Library of Congress and Fisk University Mississippi Delta collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Library of Congress and Fisk University Mississippi Delta collection 1941-1943
AFC 1941/002
Archive of American Folk Song
Fisk University
493 items; 1 container plus 1 oversize; 4 linear feet.
350 manuscript items.
10 sound discs: analog, 78 rpm, mono.; 12 in.
87 sound discs: analog, 78 rpm, mono.; 16 in.
46 negative prints: black and white; 54 x 37 cm and smaller.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists of a portion of the materials generated by a joint field project -- the Coahoma County, Mississippi, field project, 1941-1942 -- undertaken by Alan Lomax, Assistant in Charge of the Archive of American Folk Song at the Library of Congress, and Fisk University faculty members including Charles S. Johnson, John Wesley Work, and Lewis Wade Jones. Field recordings were made of secular and religious music, sermons, children's games, jokes, folktales, interviews, and dances documenting the expressive culture of an African American community in Coahoma County, Mississippi. Some audio recordings were made by Alan Lomax and John W. Work at Work's home in Nashville, Tennessee; and a few were recorded by Lomax in Arkansas. The collection includes recording logs, reports, and correspondence related to the project. Also included are negative photostats of song transcriptions by John W. Work (1943), including some songs that were recorded on this project.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Botkin, Benjamin Albert, 1901-1975--Correspondence.; Edwards, Honeyboy; Hemphill, Sid, 1876-1963; House, Son; House, Son--Correspondence.; Johnson, Charles Spurgeon, 1893-1956; Johnson, Charles Spurgeon, 1893-1956--Correspondence.; Johnson, George; Jones, Lewis Wade, 1910-1979; Jones, Lewis Wade, 1910-1979--Correspondence.; Jones, Thomas Elsa--Correspondence.; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002--Correspondence.; Mangham, S. L.; Muddy Waters, 1915-1983; Muddy Waters, 1915-1983--Correspondence.; Schmidt, Harold C.--Correspondence.; Spivacke, Harold, 1904-1977--Correspondence.; Sturz, Elizabeth Lyttleton; Work, John W. (John Wesley), 1901-1967; Work, John W. (John Wesley), 1901-1967--Correspondence.
Organizations
Archive of American Folk Song; Fisk University
Subjects
African American children's games--Mississippi.; African American children--Mississippi--Coahoma County--Social life and customs.; African Americans--Mississippi--Delta (Region)--Folklore.; African Americans--Mississippi--Delta (Region)--Music; African Americans--Mississippi--Delta (Region)--Religion.; African Americans--Mississippi--Delta (Region)--Social life and customs.; Ballads, English--Mississippi.; Blues (Music)--1941-1950.; Blues (Music)--Mississippi--Coahoma County.; Field recordings--Arkansas.; Field recordings--Mississippi.; Field recordings--Tennessee.; Folk music--Mississippi--Delta (Region); Folk songs, English--Mississippi.; Games--Mississippi--Coahoma County.; Gospel music--Mississippi--Coahoma County.; Hymns, English--Mississippi.; Railroads--Songs and music.; Singing games--Mississippi--Coahoma County.; Spirituals (Songs)--Mississippi.; Tales--Mississippi--Coahoma County.; Toasts (African American folk poetry)--Mississippi.; Work songs--Mississippi.
Places
Coahoma County (Miss.)--Religious life and customs.; Coahoma County (Miss.)--Social life and customs.; Delta (Miss.: Region)--Social life and customs.
Titles
Coahoma County, Mississippi, field project, 1941-1942; Fisk University Mississippi Delta collection; Library of Congress / Fisk University Mississippi Delta collection
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Dr. Watts hymn singing.; Field hollers.; Field recordings.; Hymns.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Music transcriptions.; Negative prints.; Prayers.; Scores.; Sermons.; Sound recordings.; Toasts (narrative poetry)
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Graphic Images; III. Sound Recordings. The Sound Recordings series is arranged by AFS number.
Acquisition
The Archive of Folk Song at the Library of Congress accessioned the collection, the product of an Archive of Folk Song-sponsored project, in 1942.
Related Material
Correspondence and field notes related to this field project are found in John A. Lomax and Alan Lomax Papers, 1932-1942 (AFC 1933/001) and the Alan Lomax Collection (AFC 2004/004). Color, silent film footage (8 minutes and 29 seconds) from this field project includes the Mississippi Baptist Convention, children's games and songs from Friars Point, Mississippi, and the Coahoma County Training School, and a guitar performance by Honeyboy Edwards (see the Archive of American Folk Song films, 1936-1942, AFC 1990/017). Disc sleeves for some of these recordings with manuscript notes by Alan Lomax and others are located in Archive of Folk Song Audio Disc Sleeves (AFC 9999/008). Related materials may be found in the John Wesley Work, III, Collection at Middle Tennessee State University.
Online Content
Interview with former slave George Johnson, Mound Bayou, Mississippi, September 1941 is available in the online presentation, Voices from the Days of Slavery. Interview with former slave George Johnson, Mound Bayou, Mississippi, September 1941 is available in the online presentation, Voices from the Days of Slavery. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000006
Online Content
Related online content is found in the Alan Lomax Collection (AFC 2004/004) including Alan Lomax’s field notes: http://www.loc.gov/collections/alan-lomax-manuscripts/about-this-collection/
See these folders:
Alan Lomax Collection, Manuscripts, Mississippi, Tennessee and Arkansas, 1941-1942, field notes http://www.loc.gov/item/afc2004004.ms070309/
Alan Lomax Collection, Manuscripts, Mississippi, Tennessee and Arkansas, 1941-1942, field notes http://www.loc.gov/item/afc2004004.ms070315/
Alan Lomax Collection, Manuscripts, Mississippi, Tennessee and Arkansas, 1941-1942, song lyrics http://www.loc.gov/item/afc2004004.ms070353/
See also Alan Lomax’s manuscripts for his book, The Land Where the Blues Began, 1993.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Articles and Books
Lomax, Alan. The Land Where the Blues Began. Pantheon Books, New York: 1993.
Crowley, John. "Really the 'Walking Blues': Son House, Robert Johnson and the Development of a Traditional Blues." Popular Music I: Folk or Popular? Distinctions, Influences, Continuities. A yearbook edited by Richard Middleton and David Horn. Cambridge University Press, 1981.
Work, John W., Lewis Wade Jones, and Samuel C. Adams; edited by Robert Gordon and Bruce Nemerov. Lost Delta Found: Rediscovering the Fisk University-Library of Congress Coahoma County Study, 1941-1942. Vanderbilt University Press, 2005.
Sound Recordings
Songs from the collection can be found on the following compilations:
Afro-American Blues and Game Songs. AFS L4. Library of Congress, 1942.
Afro-American Folk Music from Tate and Panola Counties, Mississippi. AFS L67. Library of Congress, 1978.
Afro-American Spirituals, Work Songs and Ballads. AFS L3. Library of Congress, 1942.
Muddy Waters: The Complete Plantation Recordings. Chess M.C.A., 1993.
Negro Blues and Hollers. AFS L59. Library of Congress, 1962.
Negro Work Songs and Calls. AFS L8. Library of Congress, 1943.
Son House: Delta Blues. Biograph Records, 1991.
Scope and Content
In 1941 and 1942 the Library of Congress and Fisk University of Nashville, Tennessee, jointly undertook a sociological study of African-American communities centered in Coahoma County, Mississippi, in the Mississippi Delta region. The project resulted in a number of documents, sound recordings, and motion picture footage now held in several collections at the American Folklife Center and at other institutions.
The study was first proposed to Fisk University administrators in 1940 by faculty member John W. Work III. The idea of a partnership between Fisk University and the Library of Congress formed in April 1941. It appealed to the Archive of American Folk-Song, a section in the Library of Congress Music Division, because of its focus on a single geographic region and ethnicity, a characteristic of the field projects undertaken by Alan Lomax beginning in 1937. Alan’s August 1941 project proposal to Library administrators included the following goals:
To record Negro revivals in the region of Northwestern Mississippi in company with various members of the faculty of Fisk University. This survey recording trip is preliminary to an intensive field study of Negro folk-song in a Mississippi Delta County, to be carried out during the fall and winter by the Fisk University Sociology Department in collaboration with the Archive of American Folksong. I believe that this study will represent the first scientific study in the field of American folk-song. It will be carried out by Doctor Charles S. Johnson and his graduate students in Sociology in collaboration with the Library of Congress.
The Library of Congress would furnish equipment, supplies, and a sound engineer while Fisk University would supply field workers and carry out publications and further studies.
Typically, the Coahoma project fit precariously into Alan Lomax’s other responsibilities. In addition to administering the Archive, through the spring of 1941 Alan wrote and produced two weekly radio programs for CBS. From late-July through mid-August Lomax and other Radio Research Project team members made field recordings in North Carolina, Tennessee, Georgia, and Virginia.
On August 25, 1941, Alan Lomax and Elizabeth Lomax arrived in Nashville for consultation and project development with the Fisk University team, led by Lewis W. Jones, Charles S. Johnson, and John W. Work III. The Lomaxes, Lewis Jones, and John Ross then made an exploratory field trip from August 26 through September 3, recording twenty-five 16-inch discs on the Library’s Presto Model Y disc recorder. John Work likely joined the group for at least one of the sessions. Stopping first to record a religious service just south of Jackson, Tennessee, the team continued to Mississippi, recording in Mt. Airy, Stovall, the Morehead Plantation on Texas Island all in Coahoma County, Money in Leflore County, Mound Bayou in Bolivar County, and Lake Cormorant in DeSoto County. The recordings primarily document religious expression, but include historic country blues sessions with McKinley “Muddy Waters” Morganfield and Eddie “Son” House and one extended oral history with George Johnson, a former slave.
The group left Mississippi and drove back to Fisk University around September 6 for further project development. Alan Lomax, Elizabeth Lomax, and Lewis Jones continued toward Washington, stopping on September 7th and 8th to make disc recordings in southwestern Virginia. These recordings were accessioned into the Archive as a related collection. The Lomaxes finally returned to Washington, DC, around September 10, 1941.
The institutions agreed that the project would continue. During the winter, the Fisk University team conducted field work using supplies provided by the Library. As well, the Library authorized duplication of some of John Work’s field recordings and their accession into the Archive.
Alan Lomax was in residence at the Indiana University Summer School of Folklore beginning in late-June 1942. By July 15, however, he returned to Nashville to confer with the Fisk University team about the project. They quickly moved into the field, first to West Memphis, Arkansas, then to various locations in Coahoma County. By the second week in August the team was near Sledge, Mississippi, in the Hill Country. The 1942 component of the project yielded reports, correspondence, field notebooks, and seventy-two 16- and 12-inch discs made between July 15 and August 12, 1942. Religious expression and blues again dominated, but these genres were interspersed with tale telling, children’s songs, dance songs, oral histories, and other genres. Performers who became well-known included McKinley “Muddy Waters” Morganfield, Eddie “Son” House, David “Honeyboy” Edwards, and Sid Hemphill.
Lomax returned to Nashville around August 12. Between August 20 and August 30 he made recording trips to Smithville, Tennessee, Birmingham, Alabama, Marrowbone, Kentucky, and Saltville, Virginia. These recordings were all accessioned by the Archive as separate collections. Alan returned to Washington around August 29, 1942. It was his final recording trip for the Library of Congress. In October 1942 Alan Lomax transferred to the Office of War Information to better assist the war effort.
The project has been the source of extensive publication. The Land Where the Blues Began (1993) gives Alan Lomax’s recollections of the 1941 and 1942 trips. His Rainbow Sign (1959) highlights the sermonizing of Rev. Ribbons from 1941. Lost Delta Found (2005), edited by Robert Gordon and Bruce Nemerov, provides a critical overview of the project and includes a number of primary documents. John Szwed’s biography, Alan Lomax: The Man Who Recorded the World (2010) gives considerable insight into this period of Alan’s life, as does Ronald D. Cohen’s Alan Lomax: Assistant in Charge (2010). Stephen Wade’s The Beautiful Music All Around (2012) devotes a chapter to Bozie Sturdivant’s 1942 recordings. The Library of Congress first published sound recordings from the field trip in 1942. Since then, a steady stream of publications has emerged, including the Muddy Waters: The Complete Plantation Recordings (1993) and Son House, Delta Blues (1991), and Sid Hemphill: The Devil’s Dream (2013).
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts, 1939-1947
  - Finding aid (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - From Harold Spivacke to Harold C. Schmidt, May 2, 1939
    - From Harold C. Schmidt to Harold Spivacke, April 26, 1939
  - Correspondence, June 1941 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - From Alan Lomax to Harold Spivacke, June 1941
    - From Harold C. Schmidt to Alan Lomax, June 19, 1941
  - Correspondence, July 1941 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - From Alan Lomax to Thomas E. Jones, July 1, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, July 7, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, July 30, 1941
    - From Thomas E. Jones to Alan Lomax, July 28, 1941
  - Correspondence, August 1941 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - From Alan Lomax to John W. Work, August 23, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, August 9, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, August 11, 1941
    - From John W. Work to Alan Lomax, August 19, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to LC, Music Division, August 21, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, August 21, 1941
  - Correspondence, September 1941 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - From Jerome Wiesner to LC, Mail Division, September 3, 1941
    - From Richard Hill to LC, Music Division, September 18, 1941
    - From Jerome Wiesner to Alan Lomax, September 3, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, September 4, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Jerome Wiesner, September 5, 1941
    - From Lewis Jones to Alan Lomax, September 9, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, September 16, 1941
    - From Harold Spivacke to Richard Hill, September 17, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, September 18, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to LC, Music Division, September 18, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, September 20, 1941
    - From McKinley Morganfield to Alan Lomax, September 21, 1941
    - From Harold Spivacke to LC, Music Division, September 24, 1941
    - From Caroline Joyner to Alan Lomax, September 24, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, September 29, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, September 17, 1941
  - Correspondence, October 1941 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, October 25, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Harold Spivacke, October 27, 1941
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, October 29, 1941
    - From Son House to Alan Lomax, October 30, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Archibald MacLeish, October 7, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, October 7, 1941
    - From Harold Spivacke to Charles S. Johnson, October 22, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to LC, Music Division, October 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to LC, Music Division, October 2, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Caroline Joyner, October 3, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Harold Spivacke, October 7, 1941
  - Correspondence, November 1941 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, November 6, 1941
    - From Alan Lomax to Son House, November 12, 1941
    - From H.M. Perry to Alan Lomax, November 14, 1941
  - Correspondence, December 1941 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - From Alan Lomax to Son House, December 24, 1941
  - Correspondence, January 1942 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - From Alan Lomax to Lewis Jones, January 21, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, January 22, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Son House, January 28, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to McKinley Morganfield, January 27, 1942
  - Correspondence, February 1942 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - From Alan Lomax to Son House, February 10, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to John W. Work, February 27, 1942
  - Correspondence, March 1942 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - From Alan Lomax to LC, Music Division, March 2, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, March 2, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, March 9, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to John W. Work, March 9, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, March 12, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to McKinley Morganfield, March 17, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, March 20, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, March 23, 1942
    - From John W. Work to Alan Lomax, March 23, 1942
  - Correspondence, April 1942 (Box-folder 1/13)
    - From McKinley Morganfield to Alan Lomax, April 2, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to LC, Music Division, April 8, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, April 8, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, April 13, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, April 23, 1942
  - Correspondence, May 1942 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - From Lewis Jones to Alan Lomax, May 31, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to McKinley Morganfield, May 2, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, May 4, 1942
    - From McKinley Morganfield to Alan Lomax, April 6, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Abbott L. Ferriss, May 15, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, May 13, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, May 19, 1942
    - From Lewis Jones to Alan Lomax, May 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, May 26, 1942
  - Correspondence, June 1942 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, June 8, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Harold Spivacke, June 17, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to John W. Work, June 27, 1942
    - From John W. Work to Alan Lomax, June 25, 1942
    - From McKinley Morganfield to Alan Lomax, June 25, 1942
  - Correspondence, July 1942 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - From Thomas E. Jones to Alan Lomax, July 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Harold Spivacke, July 18, 1942
  - Correspondence, August 1942 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - From Harold Spivacke to LC, Reference Dept., August 5, 1942
    - From John W. Work to Thomas E. Jones, August 18, 1942
    - From LC, Travel to Alan Lomax, August 11, 1942
    - From LC, Music Division to Alan Lomax, August 10, 1942
    - From Harold Spivacke to Alan Lomax, August 7, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Harold Spivacke, August 4, 1942
  - Correspondence, September 1942 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - From Alan Lomax to W.P. Cantrell, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Mary Lou Brewer, September 22, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Mr. Nelson, September 29, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Will Starke, September 29, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Thomas E. Jones, September 23, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Sarah Lena Teague, September 22, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Olive Murray Pennington, September 22, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles Haffer, Jr., September 29, 1942
    - From Thomas E. Jones to Alan Lomax, September 22, 1942
    - From Thomas E. Jones to John W. Work, September 22, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Booker T. Garner, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Mrs. E.M. Davis, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles Berry, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Ruby Brown Hughes, September 22, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Asa Ware, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to David Edwards, September 5, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Larry Morris, September 16, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to M.C. Orr, September 17, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Ulysses Jefferson, September 17, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Will Head, September 18, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Lucius Smith, September 18, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Alex Askew, September 18, 1942
    - From Thomas E. Jones to Alan Lomax, September 19, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to McKinley Morganfield, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Mrs. Roy Womac, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Nellie Lee Whitehead, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Turner Johnson, Jr., September 5, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Ollie Upchurch, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Flora L. Standifer, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Ruby Ford Smith, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Alec Robertson, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Rev. McGee, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to May Lassiter, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Effie Harris, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Ruby Lee Harris, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Houston Bacon, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Dorothy Dilsewith Barry, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Annie Williams, September 21, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Thomas E. Jones, September 8, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Rev. E.M. Martin, September 5, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Son House, September 5, 1942
  - Correspondence, October 1942 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - From Sid Hemphill to Alan Lomax, October 22, 1942
    - From Benjamin A. Botkin to Harold Spivacke, October 23, 1942
    - From Benjamin A. Botkin to Thomas E. Jones, October 23, 1942
    - From Benjamin A. Botkin to Thomas E. Jones, October 26, 1942
    - From Harold Spivacke to Benjamin A. Botkin, October 27, 1942
    - From Jerome Sage to Alan Lomax, October 30, 1942
    - From Eri Douglas to Jerome Sage, October 30, 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Charles S. Johnson, October 10, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Alan Lomax, October 7, 1942
    - From Thomas E. Jones to Alan Lomax, October 19, 1942
    - From William Allen Duncan to Alan Lomax, October 4, 1942
    - From LC, Music Division to Harold Spivacke, October 1942
    - From Alan Lomax to Thomas E. Jones, October 7, 1942
    - From Lewis Jones to Alan Lomax, October 1942
  - Correspondence, November 1942 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - From Thomas E. Jones to Benjamin A. Botkin, November 19, 1942
    - From Harold Spivacke to Thomas E. Jones, November 25, 1942
    - From Benjamin A. Botkin to Thomas E. Jones, November 24, 1942
  - Correspondence, December 1942 (Box-folder 1/21)
    - From Harold Spivacke to Charles S. Johnson, December 1, 1942
    - From Charles S. Johnson to Harold Spivacke, December 8, 1942